Guide to the Brooklyn Home for Children and predecessors collection ARC.324
Brooklyn Historical Society
Brooklyn Home for Children and predecessors collection
1854-1958
Brooklyn Historical Society
Brooklyn Home for Children
ARC.324
1.25 Linear Feet in two manuscript boxes and one half manuscript box.
Annual reports and other materials from the Brooklyn Home for Children and its two predecessor institutions, the Industrial School Association of Brooklyn, E.D. and the Brooklyn Industrial School Association and Home for Destitute Children.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to users without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The source and date of acquisition for the majority of this collection are unknown. The collection was formally accessioned in 1985.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into three series by organization. Within each series, material is arranged chronologically.
Historical note
The Brooklyn Home for Children was formed in 1927 with the merger of two longstanding Brooklyn childcare organizations, the Brooklyn Industrial School Association (and Home for Destitute Children) located in Prospect Heights and the Industrial School of Brooklyn, E.D. (Eastern District) located in Williamsburg. The Brooklyn Home for Children was located at the Industrial School of Brooklyn's building at 141 South 3rd Street in Williamsburg until 1941, when the institution moved to Queens.
The Brooklyn Industrial School Association was founded in 1854 and formally incorporated in 1857 to provide education, food, and shelter to orphaned, abandoned, and otherwise impoverished children in Brooklyn. It operated schools throughout Brooklyn that enrolled several hundred students per year, as well as the Home for Destitute Children, built in 1862 on Butler Street (now Sterling Place) near Flatbush Avenue in Prospect Heights. The Association's approach to its work was expressly religious in nature, with a strong emphasis placed on Christian moral principles. It was founded by female members of several Brooklyn churches, and thereafter its staff and Board of Managers was comprised entirely of women representing the different Christian denominations of Brooklyn.
The Industrial School Association of Brooklyn, E.D. was also founded in 1854.
Related Materials
Brooklyn charitable organizations for children collection (1985.106)
Scope and Contents
This collection consists almost entirely of annual reports, which feature financial statements, summaries of activities and accomplishments for each year, lists of donations and donors, as well as the organizations' constitutions and by-laws. These reports generally do not feature the names or adoption records of any residents of the homes run by the organizations. A particular strength of the collection is its insight into society's attitudes regarding poverty during the late 19th and early 20th centuries, specifically the perceived relationship between poverty and moral depravity. There are also handwritten documents retrieved from the cornerstone of the Industrial Association of Brooklyn, E.D. building on South 3rd Street in Williamsburg. Among these documents is a list of the children resident at the home in 1877.
Annual reports; Poor -- Services for -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Children -- Institutional care; Group homes for children -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Children's shelters -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Time capsules; Programs (documents); Williamsburg (New York, N.Y.); Charity; Charity organization; Charity organization -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Prospect Heights (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Industrial School Association and Home for Destitute Children; Brooklyn Home for Children; Industrial School Association of Brooklyn, E.D.
- Series 1: Brooklyn Industrial School Association and Home for Destitute Children
  - Circular, 1854 (Box 1)
  - Annual reports, 1859-1910 (Box 1, Box 2)
    Scope and Contents
    1859-1861, 1863, 1864-1871, 1873-1896, 1898-1899, 1900-1902, 1905, 1907-1910, 1916.
  - Constitution and by-laws, 1883 (Box 1)
  - News clipping, 1914 (Box 1)
- Series 2: Industrial School Association of Brooklyn, E.D.
  - Annual reports, 1869-1914 (Box 2)
    1869, 1870-1876, 1899, 1903, 1906, 1909, 1910, 1912, 1914.
  - Cornerstone documents, circa 1877 (Box 3)
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    These items were removed in 1985 by the New York City Facilities Development Corporation for the Narcotics Addiction Control Commission in the construction of the Williamsburg Narcotics Facility. These and additional items were then given to the Brooklyn Historical Society, now the Center for Brooklyn History. See the collection's accession file for a full list of items removed from the cornerstone.
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    The two handwritten annual reports were stored rolled for many years and despite such flattening as was possible, are still somewhat difficult to handle.
    These items were enclosed in the cornerstone of the Industrial School's Williamsburg building in 1877. They include:
    -An acrostic poem about the home
    -A list of children living at the home as of September 1877
    -A letter, program, and invitation related to the cornerstone laying ceremony
    -Two blank indentures of the Association
    -Two handwritten copies of annual reports for the years 1867 and 1868
    -Lists of individuals and churches who donated money for the building.
- Series 3: Brooklyn Home for Children
  - Annual reports, 1928-1930, 1937-1938, 1958 (Box 3)
  - 100th anniversary pamphlet, 1954 (Box 3)